Finding Aid for Dance Gallery Foundation records, 1980-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dance Gallery Foundation records 1980-2008 1993-2008
Dance Gallery Foundation.
2008093 Bp2
The records in this collection relate to the Peter Sparling Dance Company (PSDC) and the Dance Gallery Studio. The Dance Gallery Foundation was founded in 1984 and sponsored three professional modern dance companies during its history; J Parker Copley Dance Company (1986-1990); Dance Gallery with Alan Lommasson (1990-1991) and the Peter Sparling Dance Company with Artistic Director Peter Sparling (1993-2008). The Dance Gallery Studio closed its doors in August 2008. The records in this collection date primarily from 1993, although the collection does also include some material from Sparling's work in the 1980s. Records in the collection include promotional materials, photographs, video tapes, class schedules, administrative files, programs, production notes, and press clippings.
5.5 linear feet
1 oversize boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Accession received through Peter Sparling. (Donor no 10092 ) in 2008
The collection is open without restriction.
The Dance Gallery Foundation began in 1984 and served as the umbrella organization for three modern dance companies in its twenty-four year history; J Parker Copley Dance Company (1986-1990); Dance Gallery with Alan Lommasson (1990-1991), and the Peter Sparling Dance Company with Artistic Director Peter Sparling (1993-2008).
Sparling began the Peter Sparling Dance Company (PSDC) as a nonprofit company, and the Dance Gallery Studio as a not-for-profit dance studio, under the auspices of the Dance Gallery Foundation in 1993. Sparling, Professor and Chair in the University of Michigan Dance Department, danced with the Jose Limon and Martha Graham Dance Companies and is experienced in dance instruction and choreography. Sparling has borrowed from Graham and Limon to create his own innovative and sensuous style of choreography.
The Company's productions included text and musical scores, as well as classical and popular music. The PSDC sought to use modern dance to express "human experience from the comic, tragic, and sublime, to the ecstatic, ethereal, and extraordinary." During Sparling's tenure as Artistic Director, the PSDC repertory included newly choreographed dances to classical works such as Gluck's Orfeo ed Euridice, Vivaldi's The Four Seasons, Schubert's Nacht und Traume, Handel's "Ombra mai fu" from Serse and "Lascia ch'io pianga" from Rinaldo, Chopin's Nocturnes and Bach's Sonata No. 3 in C Major for Unaccompanied Violin. The Company also featured contemporary works choreographed by Sparling, including productions such as Dances to Ives, The End of Shame, Possible Dances, Traffic!, Peninsula, and Chronicles and Small Comforts.
In addition to supporting the Peter Sparling Dance Company, the Dance Gallery Foundation ran and funded the Dance Gallery Studio. The studio offered adult and children's classes and workshops in modern, ballet, jazz, creative movement, contact, improvisation, hip-hop, Pilates, yoga, Tai Chi, Eurythmy, Brazilian dance, Alexander Technique, and Feldenkrais. Originally housed in Ann Arbor's Technology Center, the Dance Gallery Foundation moved to the former Ann Arbor Ball Bearing Factory in 2003, converting the former industrial space into a 5,000 square foot studio designed to accommodate dance classes, dance company rehearsals, and community outreach programming.
In addition to promoting its own company and studio, the Dance Gallery Foundation partnered with community groups and educational organizations (from elementary and high schools, to community colleges and universities) to host free or low cost workshops, educational outreach programs, lectures, and master classes.
The Dance Gallery Foundation sought financial support from a variety of sources including class fees, gifts, performance booking fees, residencies, lecture demonstrations, master classes, and grants and awards. Over the years, the Foundation also hosted a number of benefit performances and receptions in Ann Arbor, such as a series at the Earle Restaurant, designed to support the Dance Company and the Foundation. However, in August 2008, due to inadequate funding, the Dance Gallery Studio closed and the Peter Sparling Dance Company lost its permanent home. In the wake of the Studio's closing, the Dance Company planned to operate on a case-by-case basis.
The Dance gallery Foundation records measure 5.25 linear feet, including oversized materials, and date from, 1980 to 2008, with the majority of the records from the period 1993-2007. The records are primarily comprised of press clippings, programs, promotional materials, administrative files, photographs, and video, and are arranged into ten series: Administrative; Bookings; Dance Gallery Studio; Development; Press Clippings; Productions; Programs; Promotional Materials; Audio-Visual Materials, and Website.
Subjects:
Dance Gallery Studio.; Peter Sparling Dance Company.; Choreographers.; Dancers.; Dance--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Modern Dance.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dance Gallery Studio.; Peter Sparling Dance Company.; Choreographers.; Dancers.; Dance--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Modern Dance.; Sparling, Peter, 1951-; Sparling, Peter, 1951-, Performances.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative 1994-2006
  The Administrative series, 1994-2006 (1.25 linear ft.), contains general administrative notes and correspondence regarding productions and staffing, advertising plans, and copies of the Dance Gallery Studio's quarterly newsletter.
  - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Advertising (Box 1)
  - Files by Year
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 1)
    - 2003-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 2004-2005, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters 1995-2005 (Box 2)
- Bookings 1999-2006
  Materials in the Bookings series, 1999-2006 (0.2 linear ft.), include information on bookings details, solicitations, and conferences, as well as plans for bookings with the Michigan Humanities Council, the Michigan Presenters Network, and the Ohio Presenters Network.
  - General (Box 2)
  - Solicitations (Box 2)
  - Conferences (Box 2)
  - Michigan Humanities Council (Box 2)
  - Michigan Presenters Network (Box 2)
  - Ohio Arts Presenters Network (Box 2)
- Dance Gallery Studio
  The Dance Gallery Studio series, 1988-2003 (0.1 linear ft.), includes class and workshops schedules and announcements for the Studio's adult, children's, and master classes in ballet, modern, jazz, pilates, Feldenkrais, creative movement, Latin/Swing, yoga, Tai Chi, contact, hip-hop, and ballroom dancing.
  - Class Schedules (Box 2)
  - Workshops (Box 2)
- Development
  The Development series, 1990-2005 (0.1 linear ft.), contains records documenting the Dance Gallery Foundation's fundraising activities. The series includes event invitations, donor letters and solicitations, and grant applications, as well as information on corporate and individual donors.
  - Events (Box 2)
  - Grants (Box 2)
  - Friends & Director's Circle (Box 2)
- Press Clippings
  The Press Clippings series, 1980-2007 (.25 linear ft.), contains press clippings, publicity notices, event announcements, and performance reviews for the Peter Sparling Dance Company and the Dance Gallery Studio. The clippings are primarily from The Ann Arbor News, the Detroit Free Press, and Current. However there are also clippings from The New York Times and Dance World.
  - 1980-1992 (Box 2)
  - 1993 (Box 2)
  - 1994 (Box 2)
  - 1995 (Box 2)
  - 1996 (Box 2)
  - 1997 (Box 2)
  - 1998 (Box 2)
  - 1999 (Box 2)
  - 2000 (Box 2)
  - 2001 (Box 2)
  - 2002 (Box 2)
  - 2003 (Box 2)
  - 2004 (Box 2)
  - 2005 (Box 2)
  - 2006 (Box 2)
  - 2007 (Box 2)
- Productions
  Records in the Productions series, 1995-2004 (.25 linear ft.), include production notes, bookings details, and scheduling for the Peter Sparling Dance Company's productions of the Four Seasons, Orfeo, and Peninsula
  - Four Seasons (Box 2)
  - Orfeo, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Peninsula, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Programs
  The Programs series, 1994-2007 (.25 linear feet), contains performance programs for the Peter Sparling Dance Company and productions by students at the Dance Gallery Studio. Programs in this series also includes productions for which Sparling did the choreography, but in which neither he nor his company performed.
  - 1994 (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Box 3)
  - 1997 (Box 3)
  - 1998 (Box 3)
  - 1999 (Box 3)
  - 2000 (Box 3)
  - 2001 (Box 3)
  - 2002 (Box 3)
  - 2003 (Box 3)
  - 2004 (Box 3)
  - 2005 (Box 3)
  - 2006 (Box 3)
  - 2007 (Box 3)
- Promotional Materials
  The series, Promotional Materials, 1994-2007 (.25 linear ft.), includes press releases, media kits, posters, flyers, and postcards designed to provide information about the Peter Sparling Dance Company, the Dance Gallery Foundation, and the Dance Gallery Studio. The series includes oversized posters and photographs which are housed in an oversized box.
  - 1994 (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Box 3)
  - 1998 (Box 3)
  - 1999 (Box 3)
  - 2000 (Box 3)
  - 2001 (Box 3)
  - 2002 (Box 3)
  - 2004 (Box 3)
  - 2005 (Box 3)
  - 2006 (Box 3)
  - 2007 (Box 3)
  - Undated (Box 3)
  - Oversize Material (Box 6)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  In the Audio-Visuals series, 1992-2007 (2.5 linear ft.) are photographs, on paper and compact discs, and video recordings, on VHS and DVD, of performances, rehearsals, and classes, as well as materials destined for use as promotional materials. The media in this series includes moving and still images from Aerial Web, Berliner Mass, children's workshops, Chronicle & Small Comforts, Diversion of Angels, El Penintente, Four Seasons, Jealousy, Johnny Angel, Les Parisiennes, New Bach, Orfeo, Peninsula, Philistines, Popular Songs, Port, Possible Dances, Seven Enigmas, Sonata, Traffic!, and Travelogue.
  - Photographs
    - Aerial Web (Box 3)
    - Berliner Mass (Box 3)
    - Children's Workshops (Box 3)
    - Chronicle & Small Comforts (Box 3)
    - Diversion of Angels (Box 3)
    - El Penitente (Box 3)
    - Four Seasons (Box 3)
    - Jealousy (Box 3)
    - Johnny Angel (Box 3)
    - Les Parisiennes (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - New Bach (Box 3)
    - Orfeo (Box 3)
    - Peninsula (Box 3)
    - Philistines (Box 3)
    - Popular Songs (Box 3)
    - Port (Box 3)
    - Possible Dances (Box 3)
    - Seven Enigmas (Box 3)
    - Sonata (Box 3)
    - Sparling, Peter (Box 3)
    - Traffic (Box 3)
    - Travelogue (Box 3)
  - CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Dance Gallery 2001, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - PSDC April 2002, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - PSDC Photos December 2002, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Raw Capture Degas/Peninsula Performance Network 2003, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Raw Capture Peninsula at Performance Network 2003, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - DGS/PSDC Peninsula, Spring 2003, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Peninsula at Film Festival March 2004, 2 optical disks CD-R; CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Peninsula Rehearsal June 23, 2004, 3 optical disks CD-R; CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - PSDC Pictures April 26, 2004, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Peninsula at Power Center June 2004, CD-R; CD-Rs 3 optical disks (Box 4)
    - Adult Modern Photos, Summer 2006, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Dance Gallery Photos June 21, 2006, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Newsletter Photos July 2006, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Fall 2006 Photos, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Dance Gallery undated, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Earle Photos undated, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - PSDC undated, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Martin & Peter 4 Mac, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Dance Gallery Foundation Website Capture, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
  - Videotapes
    - UMS Dance Program, Did You Know, Vol. 1 February, 2003, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling, Border Crossings April 6, 2000, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company in Peninsula, Power Center June 23, 2004, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company Repertory, Performance Network August 22, 2004, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company, Gluck's Orfeo ed Euridice, Educational Presentation April 11, 2001, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - MCACA Dance/New Works--Dance Gallery/Peter Sparling & Co., Sample of Work of Interpretive Artist April 24, 1997, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Repertory Sampler--Dance Gallery/Peter Sparling & Co., 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Wildt St. Tom, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company, www.Comnet.Org/DanceGallery, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Comcast Newsmakers Peter Sparling TRT: 5 Minutes, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - 1. DGS Youth Repertory Group, Performance Network June 1, 2003, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 2. PSDC, Katz Elementary March 18, 1997, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 3. PSDC, Estabrook New Horizon February 4, 1997, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 4. PSDC, Excerpts from Repertory, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 5. PSDC, Hearts Plunder, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 6. PSDC, Orfeo and Euridice, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 7. PSDC, Orfeo ed Euridice, Michigan Theater, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 8. UMS Presents PSDC, Orfeo ed Eurdice May 19, 2001, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 9. PSDC, Berliner Mass/Seven Enigmas July 12, 1997, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 10. PSDC, General Promo Video, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 11. PSDC, Peninsula May 13, 2003, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 12. BRAVO, Celebrating the Arts in Southeast Michigan, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 13. Peter Sparling: Heidi Stoeckley, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 14. PSDC, Excerpts from Repertory (Orfeo, Chronicles), 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 15. PSDC, Adventures in New Media July 10, 2000, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 16. PSDC, Excerpts from Repertory, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 17. PSDC, "Winter" from Vivaldi Four Seasons, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 18. PSDC, Diversion of Angels/Chronicles, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 19. DGS, The Wildt Street Space, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 20. UMS Presents PSDC, The Orfeo ed Euridice Residency, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 21. DGS, Bernie $ Dottie July 15, 2000, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 22. PSDC, Traffic !/Possible Dances/Orfeo Suite January 11, 2001, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 23. PSDC, NEA Proposal FY 2001 Access/Dance, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 24. DGS, Christina Sears, Girlstown Summer Camp 2002, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 25. Peter Sparling, The Institute for Humanities, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 26. PSDC & DGS, Promotional Video, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 28. PSDC & DGS, Master GLPAA Promo Video, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 29. PSDC & DGS, Repertory Sampler, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 30. PSDC, "Move It" Dress Rehearsal June 24, 1992, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 31. PSDC, Travelogue (excerpts), 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 32. PSDC, Promotional Video September 10, 1998, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 33. PSDC, "Possible Dances", 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 34. DGS, Moscow Ballet Nutcracker/Kid's 2002, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 35. DGS, Moscow Ballet/Kid's 2001, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 36. DGS, Nutcracker/Academy of Dance Arts 2001-2002, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 37. Peter Sparling, MCACA Samples of Work 1995, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - 38. DGS & Janet Lilly, Storybook, Michigan Theater, April 23, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
  - Digital Video Discs (DVDs)
    - Complete Peninsula, DVD-R (Box 5)
    - DGS/PSDC, Winter Wonderland, December 5 & 6 2003, 1 optical disks DVD (Box 5)
    - Dance Gallery Studio, Spring Showcase, May 12 2002, 1 optical disks DVD (Box 5)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company, Promotional Video, Peninsula Part II, Les Parisiennes 2004, 1 optical disks DVD-Rs (Box 5)
    - Peter Sparling, The End of Shame August 8, 2005, 1 optical disks DVD-Rs (Box 5)
    - Peter Sparling, Odes (Studio Version) 2005, 1 optical disks DVD-Rs (Box 5)
- Archived Website
  The Website series, 1998 (2 CD-Roms) includes screen captures of the Dance Gallery Foundation/Peter Sparling Dance Company website. The PSDC/DGF website includes information on the Foundation's activities, donor program, and internship opportunities; the Dance Gallery Studio's class schedules, fees, teacher profiles, and studio information; and the Peter Sparling Dance Company's schedule, repertory, events, company member profiles, mission statement, and educational outreach opportunities, as well as biographical information on Peter Sparling. The website capture included all information available on the core Dance Gallery Foundation website, but excluded content available on external websites, such as merchandise sold by Café Press or class and company photographs offered for sale by Best Ever Media. The first website capture was done by Nancy Deromedi on July 9, 2008, and the second was done by Kate Donovan, using HTTrack, on December 16, 2008. The website address at the time of both captures was http://www.dancegalleryfoundation.org/.
  - Peter Sparling Dance Gallery Foundation Website Snapshots July 9, 2008, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
  - Dance Gallery Foundation Website capture December 16, 2008, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
Related Material
Researchers should note that related material on Peter Sparling can be found in the Peter Sparling Papers, also located at the Bentley Historical Library. This collection includes Sparling's personal papers, as well as materials on his dance training, performance, and teaching, including choreography notes and sketches, correspondence, clippings and reviews, programs, photographs, posters, and video and film of performances.